hey everyone welcome back to our Channel
I am back with another interesting topic
in the Tosca automation playlist
now we are going to discuss about how we
can clone a particular workspace in
Tosca
first let's understand what is this
cloning and why it is required
so cloning as the name suggests is
basically creating a copy of your
workspace which you have created earlier
now if you are working in a team there
would be several team members who would
be working or who need to work on the
same Tosca workspace so we need to
provide a copy of our main workspace to
each one of them right
so that each one of us in the team are
working on the same workspace
now the problem here is you can't just
copy and paste your workspace into
another folder or into another machine
so that will not work because each time
you create a workspace in Tosca it
creates a unique ID of that particular
workspace so if you copy that workspace
and paste it into a different machine
then it will still be referring to the
same ID which was created originally
so ultimately what will happen is if
multiple people are working on that
copied workspace then your workspace
will get locked because two processes
will be trying to access the same bug
space with the same ID
and that is why you need to basically
clone a workspace instead of copying the
workspace okay so there is a particular
tool which Tosca has provided through
which you can clone any number of
workspaces from your main workspace
and that is the process which you need
to follow whenever you are working in a
team and you need to distribute your
workspace to all the different Oscar
development machines where people can
log in and then start working on their
own workspace okay
so let's see how we can do this cloning
process
so for this we are going to use a
multi-user workspace which is this multi
demo okay and we are going to create
clones of these multi demo Tosca
workspace which we have created
so this tool is basically a exe which is
present in your Tosca Commander uh
folder directory where you have
installed it okay
so this tool is called TC workspace
cloneutil.exe
and as I said it is present uh in the
commander home directory okay so if I go
here
into my file explorer and I just type
Commander underscore home and then
percentage it will take me to that
particular folder okay and now here if I
search PC work
space clone util
okay so here you will see this is the
file or this is the tool a utility tool
which has been provided by Tosca
Commander okay and it is present in your
installation directory so it is called
TC workspace clone util
now you cannot directly run this as an
exe okay here you have to use the
command line tool in order to run this
particular uh util tool to clone your
particular workspaces it also needs some
arguments which we need to pass okay so
for that what I have done is I have
created a batch file okay so if I go
ahead and I edit this file you will be
able to see what's inside this so the
first command is uh to go into the
command Commander home directory and the
next command is basically calling that
exe and then passing the parameters
so the first parameter which it accepts
is the workspace which you want to clone
okay so Dash workspace and then you need
to give the path the complete path
and then the out parameter this is
basically uh the output directory folder
okay where it will be creating the
Clones so you need to give that
particular path
and then the count uh here you need to
specify how many clones you want to
create okay so I want to create five
clones you can give 10 15 20 50 whatever
number you want uh to create loans for
this particular workspace okay so these
are the two commands which will be
executed as part of this batch file okay
you can also go individually into the
command prompt and go ahead and execute
uh one by one or you can just create the
batch file which will automatically
execute this right
so let's quickly go ahead and execute
this now as you can see I have already
created a clones folder here and I have
given this particular path in my um in
my command okay
so what I'm going to do I'm going to
double click on this batch file
and you will see here it will open this
command prompt so in the First Command
it went into that particular folder okay
and then it started the cloning process
it cloned uh 5 or it created Five clones
for that particular workspace
okay and now if I go ahead and the
Clones directory you will see that the
five different clones of that particular
workspace has been created in different
folders
now if I go into each folder it is in
itself a workspace okay and it has got
its own workspace ID
and now we just need to copy this okay
into different development machines
which will be used by each Tosca team
member to work on its own workspace
now all of this workspace are still
connected to the same repository okay so
even if everyone is working on their own
workspace they are checking in and
checking out from the same Repository
so this is how you can clone different
workspaces from your main workspace so
that it can be used in different Oscar
machines
that's all for this particular video if
you have any questions then please leave
it in the comments
if you like this video then please
subscribe to our Channel
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next video